$$ All statistics in this
film are from US Government Studies.
[trumpet sound]
[helicopter whirring]
Today, the latest weapons coupled with the fighting skill of the American soldier
stand ready on the alert
all over the world to defend this country.
You, the American people, against aggression.
This is The Big
Picture.
Now to show you part of The Big Picture,
here is Sgt. Stuart Queen.
- The privilege of serving
the United States in uniform,
is no longer
limited to men.
[drum roll]
♪ [music]
♪
[Woman] The value placed bythe Women's Army Corps
on meticulous grooming and feminine grace
is one of the first lessons learned by the recruit.
[Man on PA] There were demands that would require of her
perfect physical health and stamina.
- Ladies, count.- [All] One, two, three, four...
one, two, three, four.
[Nurse] I'm sure you've all heard the saying,
"There's a right way, a wrong way,and the Army way."
♪ Duty is calling you and me ♪
♪ we have a date with destiny ♪
♪ Ready... ♪
♪ the WACs are ready ♪
♪ Their pulse is steady ♪
♪ A world to set free ♪
♪ Service ♪
♪ we're in it heart and soul ♪
♪ Victory is our only goal ♪
♪ We're looking for ♪
♪ Computer specialists ♪
♪ Plane technicians ♪
♪ Plumbers...Carpenters... ♪
♪ Electricians...Art illustrators... ♪
♪ Statisticians... ♪
♪ Air controllers...Security police... ♪
♪ Auto Mechanics...Fire chiefs... ♪
♪ Look up ♪
♪ We look up to in the Air Force ♪
[Woman on PA] 2-1-2 radar contact
Turn right heading one-five-zero
[Announcer] With the fog-bound helicopterhanging on your every word,
it doesn't matter whether you're a man or a woman, only that you're good.
- Coming up slowly...
♪ Be all that you can be. . . ♪
- [Pilot] Thanks for your help.
- Roger.
♪ 'Coz we need you in the Army ♪
[helicopter blades whirring]
[Female Pilot] I'm flying in a helicopter right now.
[machine gun firing]
Don't second‐guess yourself. It's a
lot of work, but it's totally worth it.
$$ The Invisible War
♪ [music] ♪
[Kori Cioca] I would just always seethe movies of the military
and I just knew that was me.
That's what I wanted to do. That's what I wanted to be.
There was a waiting list for the Navy over a year
and I knew I didn't want to wait that long
So, I had a friend who told me
about the Coast Guard
and I went to the Coast Guard
and they said that they could get me in
within a month so I said,
"Okay, ship me off."
- I had tried college and I had a good job
at a vineyard in East Texas.
I bought my own little house.
The military was something
I always wanted to do.
I come from a military family.I was always taught
that it's every citizen's dutyto join the military.
If you can, you should. So, I want to go ahead
and join and start a career.
[aircraft taking off]
[Robin Lynn Lafayette] I joined the Air Force. I was 17 years old.
I had a boyfriend that encouraged me
to go in so that's what I did.
My mom signed, gave me permission to go.
[Lt. Ariana Klay] When I was in high school,
I was impressed withthe marines that I had met.
There used to be a lieutenant colonelthat used to run laps
around the track after soccer practice.
And, he said,
"You'd be perfect for the Marine Corps
'cause you're really fit and smart
and that's what the Marine Corps needs."
The professionalism, the camaraderie,
everything about it inspired me.
- After I graduated high school,
I left for Orlando, Florida,
which was the first time I was
ever on an airplane in my whole life.
[chuckles]
Initially, it was just wanting to go see the world
'cause I'm from a really small town.
I had a college scholarshipto go play basketball
but I instead, opted to go into the military.
So, that's what I chose to do.
- [Lt. Elle Helmer] I come from a long line of military lineage.
Somebody from every generation
on both sides of the family,
all the way back to the revolutionary war,had served in the armed forces.
I chose the Marine Corps because
no one in my family had ever done it.
- I love putting on the uniform every day
and, you know, just getting out there
and giving it my all.
It's a very proud feeling.
[Everyone] 1, 1000... 2, 10003, 1000
He's a piece...
- I would have done boot camp
over and over again.
It was great, the camaraderie,the discipline, everything it taught you.
Who I wanted to be.That's what they taught you there.
- Obviously it was different
taking a shower with 80 different people
all of a sudden 'cause I was pretty shy.
But, just a great experience.
I was a 4‐0 sailor. Every singlereport done on me was excellent, great.
I knew what I needed to do in my job.I was a great team leader.
[Jessica Hinves] I really enjoyed the whole challenge of it.
I got several different awards and kudos.
It was mainly men.
I loved that I could blend in and keep up with the guys
and work as hard as they did.
[cheers and applause]
- [Lt. Ariana Klay] The Naval Academywas challenging.
The education was top‐notch.
In my senior, I was selected to be in
one of the top 30 leadership positions
by the company grade officers there.
- [Trina McDonald] After basic, I went to Naval Security Group in Adak, Alaska.
I remember getting there, you know, issued a parka, I got set up in my room.
And then he took me to the bar,
which was in our barracks
and sat down at a table where it was
me and about ten other guys.
And, you know, I kind of felt like a piece
of meat on a slab at that point.
And I'd never wanted to turn around
and leave so much in my life.
But I couldn't.
- [Child[ Hey, mama.
[ball bouncing]
- [Kori] Go get it this time.
- Okay.
- [Kori] Get him, get him.
- [Rob] Hey, you give me that ball.
- [Kori] Give it to him derby style. Get him.
[child laughing]
- [Rob McDonald] I met Kori
December 17th of 2007.
I was on watch
when she got to the station
and she kind of just blew me away
when she walked in.
- Cookies, right?
Is it good you ordered?
Okay. Thank you.
- The command told us that
she was coming
and there were some issues
but none of the crew knew exactly
what had happened.
And I didn't find out for a long time.
- For mommy?Where's the heart?
- He loved his job. And it's kind of like
he gave it up for me.
- She loved the Coast Guard
more than I did.
She wanted to make it a career,
but seeing how they treated her,
I didn't want to stay in.
I did it and then I did my extra year
and I got out.
I couldn't believe
what had happened to her,
and what she had went through.
- [Kori Cioca] I was stationed in Saginaw River, Michigan.
I was the only female in my section.I had a supervisor.
It got to the place where I'd getcalls at three o'clock in the morning
and he'd be drunk at a bartelling me to come get him.
And I'm like, "I cant, I'm in bed,"and he would then threaten me.
I'd walk in from training and he'd be sleeping in my bed.
When we went to
one of the higher‐ups
in the chain of command,
they were all like his drinking buddy
and they told me just because
I didn't like somebody,
they weren't going to switch me
away from this guy.
It was in the evening, around taps,
and he had unlocked the door
and he had come in,
and he had an erection
and he tried to get me to touch him.
I took my right hand and
I pushed him in the chest
and started to yell for the other guys
to kinda hear me, "Hey, hey, hey."
He hit me across
the left side of my face.
I remember holding the closet thinking,
"What just happened?"
And my face hurt so bad.
And when we wentto the command about it,
me and this petty officer who saw my face,
they just let it wait 'cause they didn't want any problems going on.
A couple of weeks later, I needed the key to do my cleanup
so I knocked on his door
and he said,
"Okay, yeah. come on in here.
It's in here."
And I said, "No, no, no,
I'm gonna wait out here."
And he said screamed at me
and he made me come in,
and he grabbed my arm
[sobbing]
and he raped me at his berthing area.
- Everything came to a complete change
the day that I was raped.
- I got there in February
and by April
I was drugged and raped
for the first time.
- I had a cold or pneumonia-like symptoms
and so they sent me to get checked out.
And, while I was waiting to be examined,
he came in and he helped himself.
- He said he was going to the bathroom
and he came into my room
and that's when he raped me.
- The entire time I was screaming
and yelling for help and for him to stop,
nobody came to the door,
nobody came to help me,
came to my rescue or anything.
- They made it very, very clear
that if I said anything,
they were going to kill me, you know,
and then of course,
I didn't have anyone to go talk to
because the people that
were perpetrating me were the police.
- It was my first time ever,
and I've had a tough time
convincing myself that I'm still a virgin.
- If this is happening to me, I can only
imagine surely I'm not the only one,
in which I find out later, going through
the claims process, that I wasn't.
$$ Over 20% of female veterans have been
sexually assaulted while serving.
- It's just after three am, I see
a shadow of a human head over my body.
- Next thing you know,
like I wake up and like he's on top of me.
- He pushed my legs apart
and put himself on top of me
and started pulling at my shirt.
- And I wake up, and he's on top of me.
He's already penetrated me.
- I was drugged. I remember
the sounds, the smell.
- He put his locked and loaded
45 at the base of my skull,
and gauged the bolt so that I knew
that it was around chambered.
- All I could do was continue
to concentrate on breathing.
- He slammed my head
against the concrete wall
and very forcefully had sex with me.
- I just went to my tent,
pulled the sleeping bag over my head
and cried myself to sleep.
- So, within that two-week period,
he raped me five times.
- When we got tested,
I had trich and gonorrhea
and I was pregnant.
- And he did it. He raped me.
- In 1991, in Congressional testimony,
it was estimated that 200,000 women
had been sexually assaulted so far
in the US Military.
If you take into account that women
don't report because of
the extreme retaliation and that was,
you know, more than a decade ago.
I would say you could easilydouble that number
and it's probably somewhere near abouthalf a million women have now been
sexually assaulted in the US military.
- Well, according to the
Department of Defense,
3230 women and men reported assault
in the last fiscal year, fiscal year 2009
But they also admit, D.O.D itself,
that 80% of sexual assault survivors
do not report. So if you do the math,
16,150 service members
were assaulted,which is an extraordinary number.
[vial dropped]
[cluttering sound]
- We have more in the cars, Rob.
There's some of it here, too.
This all was prescribed
in the last three to four months.
This is Proxatine, this is Seroquel,
Seroquel...
Citolopram, this is Xanax.
I'm tired of taking all these meds.
I just want the VA to fix my jaw.
I was having the most horriblepain in my face,
so I went to the dentist because I thought it was my teeth
or something was wrong. The doctor came in after the X‐ rays
and asked me if I had been in a car accident.
When he hit me in my face,
he dislocated my jaw
and it sent both of my disks
forward in my face so I don't have
any disks where they should be in my face.
They told me I'd probably need a
partial bone replacement.
From where my bone had been laying
on my nerves for so long,
it's starting to actually disintegrate.
I've been on a soft diet
for five years now.
I can't eat the foods that I used to eat.
Everything is mashed potatoes, Jell-o.
[wind whistling]
Well, I can go out
during the summer time,
spring time... if it's warm.
If it's too cold outside,
it's usually just Rob and Shea
go outside.
When it's really cold,
it's like my jaw would just lock up.
I just stand, watch from the window
and hear about the stories when they come in.
- [Man on IVR] We are sorry, but due to a large volume of calls
and unusually long wait times,
counselors are unable to
answer your call at this time.
[Woman on IVR] Please stay on the line,the calls will be answered
in the order received.
[Man on IVR] 15 minutes could saveyou hundreds on car insurance.
[Woman on IVR] It's the Saint Louis holiday tradition.
[Colbie Caillat playing on background]
[Man on VA] Hey, this is Stan.
- Hi Stan, I just wanted to check
the status of my VA claim.
[Stan] It's still on file on admissions, let me check.
- Okay --
- [Stan] It looks like it's about a year old now.
- Yes, it is. Okay it's still pending?
Did it say what status it was in?
- [Stan] Well, it looks like they've got all the information that they need
but it still hasn't movedto the rating board yet.
- Okay.
- [Stan] Thank you for calling ma'am.You have a good day.
- You too. Thank you.
This is the stuff they prescribed me
for migraines
even though I don't have migraines.
So, I was looking online
and there are actually other vets
at the age of like, 25
and they would actually just die
because their body wasn't processing
because the mixture of the Seroquel,
the Gavapentin, the some kind of anxiety,
which was the Xanax
and, there was something else,
an antidepressant.
The mixtures of that stuff,
which is everything I have here that
other vets were taking
and they have died.
[door shuts]
- [Hannah] Hey, baby girl. Hey, hey.
- Sit.
- Both my dad
and my brother are prior Navy
and now Army National Guards.
And it's kind of like it follows in the
family and follows the footsteps.
I was excited and completely
just hyped up about going.
All my family was proud of me.
My dad is my biggest hero.
- [Sgt. Major Jerry Sewell] I told her, I said,
"You are going to be taken care of."
And I guess that's one of the hard things
that I have to accept because
I told her that she would be.
It was in February, we got a call.
$$ On February 1st 2008,
Hannah was locked in a hotel room
and raped by a fellow recruit. $$
- Once he was done,
he rubbed his hand
all over my entire body
and told me, he said,
"I own all of this."
And I was just absolutely scared,didn't know what to do.
I called my dad.
- One of the first things she said is,
"Dad, I'm no longer a virgin."
And I said, "What happened?"
And she said, "I was raped."
And I said,
"Hannah, you're a virgin because
he took something from you
that you didn't give."
[sobbing]
I said, "So, don't ever think you're not."
- My main nerve in my spine
was pinched in three places
and my hips were rotated.
I could barely walk. I had collapsed due
to muscle spasms in my back
because my back
was injured during the rape.
- [Admiral Anthony Kurta] My title isDirector of Military Plans
and Personnel policy for the Navy.
We have specifically trained
judge advocates.
Our Navy lawyers, in our naval criminal
investigative service,
those investigators are all specifically
trained in sexual assault.
Any report of a sexual assault
is fully investigated
in the United States Navy.
- They didn't take care of it.
For a year and a half,
they were tracking down witnesses.
They had all these students there and they could have locked them down
and said, "Hey you're on legal hold
until I get a statement."
And they didn't. Hannah went through
three investigators.
It was like, "Okay I'm given this case."
That's what it sort of felt like.
"Oh, alright I'm given this case.
I got to take care of it."
"Oh well, this is a navy one.
I really don't have
the time to deal with it."
- Females would come up
to their commanders
or their NCOs and say that they were
either sexually assaulted or abused
and I don't think it was taken seriously.
I think a lot of times
a cursory investigation was done
and they were basically told
to just suck it up.
- I remember bringing in
a young service member
who had been brutally raped,
and bringing her in to see her command,
and trying to make sure that this
young girl was taken care of properly.
And this idiot, chewed her out for crying,
told her to stop crying over spilt milk.
- A lot of times,
the credibility of the witness
was called into account.
Had the potential victim,
had she made claims
like this in the past?
There was a lot of witch hunting going on.
- I was ordered to advise a victim
of her rights
for false statement when I knew
that she wasn't lying.
I was asked to bring her in
and advise her of her rights,
like a criminal and interrogate her
for false statement,
"until I got the truth out of her."
If a woman makes a rape complaint,there are always people asking
what she was doing there,
what she was wearing,
whether she had a boyfriend or not.
- If rape cases came in,
they were never given to women.
The men always took care of those.
- Why is that?
- Because we were too sympathetic.
- Is that what they said to you?
- Uh-hmm.
"We couldn't see what was really going on
because we always took the woman's side."
- I was told I should have been
a social worker.
I had no business being
in the police field.
There was a lot of resistance there
toward the idea that victims should be
afforded some kind of sensitivity.
It was almost a laughing matter.
- We have given specific training
and continual training
to our NCIS,
Navy Criminal Investigative Service,
those investigators on how best to
respond and to investigate those crimes.
- They told me they lost my rape kit
and my nurse examiners report and the
pictures from the bruising on my arm.
- [Amy] They lost these things?
That's what they told me.
They told me that they had lost them.
And me being me,
I decided to do a little digging
of my own and I spoke with
NCIS headquartersin Washington DC,
and they have all the evidence.
- [Amy] So what does this mean?
- Because the case is already closed,
there's nothing they can do.
- [Susan Burke] What we hearagain and again
from soldiers who have been raped,
is that as bad as it was being raped,
what was as bad, if not worse,
was to receive professional retaliation
in their chosen career,
merely because they were raped.
- When you report something,
you better be prepared
for the repercussions.
- If a man gets accused of rape,
it's a set‐up.
The woman is lying.
- I could choose to report it,
but if they found out
what I was saying wasn't to be truthful,
then I would be reduced in rank.
- You could lose your rate,
you could lose rank,
you could lose your school,
if you file a false report.
So do you want to file a report?
[Laughs]
- Even with the rape kit and everything,
and my friend catching him raping me,
they still don't believe me.
- I reported it two different times
to my squad leader
and he told me that there was nothing
he could do about it
'cause I didn't have any proof.
- They actually did charge me
with adultery.
I wasn't married. He was.
- They took me before
my lieutenant commander.
He says, "You think this is funny?"
I said, "What do you mean?"
He's like, "Is this all a joke to you?"
And he goes, "You're the third girl
to report rape this week."
"Are you guys like, all in cahoots,
you think this is a game?"
- [Man on IVR] We are sorry, but due to a large volume of calls
and unusually long wait times,
counselors are unable to answer your call at this time.
- [Woman Operator] Your name, please?
- It's Kori Danielle McDonald.
[Woman Operator] Okay, I showthat we've got a claim
open for non‐service‐connected disability pension, depression, TMJ,
bilateral disk condition,PTSD, nerve‐damage.
It's at the rating boardin Cleveland.
- Okay, and how long does that
usually take?
- [Woman Operator] Anywhere from 102 to 139 days.
- Really?
- [Woman Operator] And that's justan estimated timeline.
- A hundred and thirty-nine days?
I mean that's like --
I've already been waiting like 14 months.
What the fuck is going on up there?
What the fuck is going on with the VA?
Like, my shit is new?
And it's 14 months?
I bet if we were there in person,
they would have to do something.
[door shuts]
[car starts]
[car revvs]
Are you ready? Say ready.
Do you know where we're going?
- [Both] Where are we going?
- Church.
- No, to the doctor.
Why are we going to the doctor?
- [Kori] What hurts on mommy?
- Face.
- [Kori] My face, that's right.
- You're gonna want to get on 75 North.
- On 75 North?
- Yup.
This goes everywhere with me,
and then this goes everywhere with me.
You always have protection
with Jesus but sometimes
you need just a little bit more.
[Kori Bye.
- I love you.
- [Kori] Be good.
- [Baby] Mommy, mommy.
- Mommy will be out in a minute,
alright?
Say 'bye to Mama.
- [Baby] Bye bye.
[Rob McDonald]
In doctor's appointments,
I come to every one just in case
she gets worked up
and she's uneasy around men already.
So, I have my phone up on me.
She already has, I tell her to have
a text message or me on speed dial
if she needs to get out of there.
[Baby babbling]
We'll get you a big surprise.
- [Rob] Come on, how did it go?
- Uh, it went good. They --
- [Baby] Mama...
- Of course they -- they ordered a
back X-ray instead of a face X-ray but...
Here, here's some make up.
They should have --
they should know...
They should know
what's wrong with me.
Like read my stuff
and you'll see it's my face.
It's not my back, it's not my legs,
it's not my arms, it's my face.
- So the people who need your proof
don't even know what your case
is even about.
- Like I don't even know
why we wasted the gas money
the trip, anything.
It was completely a waste of time.
What a good Veterans Day, right?
- [Rob] Yeah, it's a perfect way to spend it.
- Yeah, screw it.
[Dog barking]
- Alright, it's around midnight
on October 24th,
and Kori woke up, myselfand our baby.
[Rob] She woke up screaming.So, it's been happening quite a bit.
[Baby babbling]
- [Kori] Go, go go.
[leaves crunching]
- [Kori] Oh! [clapping]
- [Baby] One more.
- [Kori] I'm sorry I woke you up,
but it's fun, right? You're having fun.
- [Baby] Let's put more.
- [Kori] Yeah, let's put more.
- [Rob] I think Kori almost likes it better because it's quiet
and you don't really knowwhat to run into every night.
[Leaves crunching]
[Rain pouring]
- Because it was in isolated duty station,
They were in charge and we were
just kind of like, cattle, so...
That was he first time I was drugged and raped, I was in this room
with some of my friendsand I only had like one or two drinks.
And I went and laid down.It was like instantly,
I was not feeling well and it came
to having a pillow over my head
and my friend raping me.
And that went on repeatedly.
You had to call an operator to get a line off base.
So, they listen to your phone calls
so they were screened.
And I used to call my dad and begged him
to get me out of there.
He would always ask me, you know, "Hon, well what's wrong?"
And I'm like,"I can't tell you what's wrong,"
because the people that were listening
to our phone calls,
were the same people that could hurt me.
- [Russell Strand] Most sex offenders are hunters.
Just like any hunter,
they study their prey,
they study their movements,
they study their behaviors,
they study the environment.
- [Staff Sgt. Stace Nelson] You have rapists that prey on other human beings
They stalk them,
they wait until the victim
is at the most vulnerable point in time
to perpetrate their crimes.
- A lot of times the victim is somebody
that the suspect is very familiar with
and they're very aware
of what's going on.
- [Russell Strand] Most sex offenders have this hidden persona
that nobody ever sees except for the victim.
Therefore when they're caught
or if somebody reports,
people don't tend to believe that
because they don't see
the typical sex offender.
- If it's an officer, it's an officer
that has habitually,
in the past, preyed on an enlisted.
They would do it once, they would get away with it,
and then they think,
"Wow this is pretty easy,I'm going to try it again."
- Particularly for a savvy perpetrator,
to work with within a relatively
closed system, like the military,
it becomes a prime target rich
environment for a predator.
$$ A navy study found that 15 percent
of incoming recruits
$$ attempted or committed rape
before entering the military.
$$ Twice the percentage of the
equivalent civilian population.
- When I was discharged, I moved to
Seattle where things got really bad.
I started to lose everything.
I was homeless, there was addiction,I was selling drugs, packing a gun.
- Forty percent of homeless
female veterans have been raped
while they were serving.
They spin into such depression
and abuse that they can't hold jobs,
they can't hold their lives together,
and they end up on the streets.
[water gushing]
- [Trina McDonald] My partner, Amy, I met her a few years ago.
I was going and trying to do
some stuff at the gym.
And uh... [chuckles]
[Amy Rosaaen‐McDonald] When I first saw Trina,
I was at the gym and I look over
and it was like the universe was like --
Like, "Oh!" And in my head,
I was like, "Oh, there you are."
Well I knew there was something
"special" about her
- [Trina] [chuckles] Wow!
- For sure.
- [Trina] When we first started dating,
it was hard.
The biggest hurdle
was not taking PTSD, personally.
It does get really stressful.
[in-game machine gun firing]
- [Trina] [whispering] What's that?
- A trader.
- Trader?
Like a vendor?
- Yeah.
- Not like, "I'm a traitor like you,
bastard traitor!" that kind of thing.
[Amy laughing]
Okay.
If I've ever lived with anybody,
it's just been with that person.
So when I moved in,
it was like "Oh, my God",
you know, it was Amy --
- [Amy] I'm not just moving in with Amy, - [Trina] Three boys...
I'm moving in with an entire family.
[Trina] And I was like,
"Oh my God."
So, they were so used
to such open space,
and with my PTSD,
we had some moments.
- I'm sort of sad to have never known
Trina beforehand
- Yeah.
when she was sort of in her prime.
Now she's anxious and sad a lot.
$$ Women who have been raped
in the military have a PTSD rate
$$ higher than men
who've been in combat.
[Trina] I'm gonna go --
I'm gonna go protect you, Mitch.
Ceecee, come. Let's go.
-[Trina] A lot of times, like if we're outdoing something, you know,
Mitch will be like, checking in like,"Oh, it's okay Trina. It's alright."
I'm appreciative of it, you know,
but it makes me really sad
that here's this little 11‐year‐old boy
that's watching out for my wellbeing.
It hurts. I want it to go away, you know,
and it doesn't go away.
[men shouting]
♪ [loud, intense music] ♪
[THUD!]
- [Russell Strand] I think the menthat we attract in the military,
you know, we've got the Army of One,
you know, Be All You Can Be,
all those themes we've had
throughout the years,
are very, very heavily masculine.
Masculinity cannot be victimized,
because if you're a leader,
if you're a masculine person,
and you're victimized, then you're weak.
The problem is anybody can be a victim of sexual assault.
- [Michael Matthews] I joined the servicein 1972.
The military is a great way of life.
I got to see the world, I got educated.
I loved the military. I was 19
and I went to the chow hall alone,
and the next things I know,
I was laying on the ground,
and I was struck from behind,
and two guys were holding me down,
and one guy
was pulling my pants down.
And, you know, he was
taking care of his business.
And you know, I struggled,
and I was being struck and hit
and told to shut up or they'd kill me.
And I see how it destroyed my life.I mean, I've been married three times.
Luckily, I have a wife right now who
I've been married to for 25 years.
- You start wondering
and you start sort of,
you know either coming up
with reasons why things
are the way they are.
And for a long time, I kept thinking,
I don't know, there's something else.
- [Michael] I had never told anybody in over thirty years.
I decided to tell my wife.
It was the scariest moment of my life.
I was going to tell my wife,
she was going to leave me,
and I would be lost without her.
I mean, honest to God,
I couldn't get up every morning
without my wife, you know.
And I told her.
- I felt horrified, and I felt sad
and I felt angry, and you know,
along the course of the evening,
feelings just started to surface
that were probably just simmering
for a very, very long time.
- And she put her arms around me
and we both sat there and sobbed
It was like, this great weight
had been lifted off of me.
- [Brigadier Gen. Loree Sutton] I think it's important to recognize
that military sexual trauma is not limited to women,
and in fact, when it comes
to the absolute numbers,
because of the proportion of men,
in much larger numbers than women,
actually the numbers are even greater.
- [Russell Strand] I think one of the last bits of research,
showed that about 1% of males
had been victims of sexual assault
within the past year in the military.
That equals to about 20,000.
- You would get labeled
as a 'buddy‐fucker'
and that's not a nice term
to be related to.
So, it's just one of those things
that you just don't talk about
or you don't bring to anybody's attention.
You just kind of keep it to yourself.
- It's really, really hard to forget.
You know up until now, I still --
they live in my head, you know.
I can hear them laugh,
I can see their faces,
I can see what they're doing to me.
- I felt scared and I was scared
to tell my friends,
the people that really knew me
the truth about what happened.
- The shame, as bad as it is
for women
is even worse for men, because
it's all tied in with homophobia.
- The people who are
doing the raping are not gay.
That's not the problem. They're worried
about gays in the military.
The gays are not the rapists.
They are heterosexual men
for the most part.
- This is not an issue
of sexual orientation,
this is simply an issue of power
and violence.
Male sexual predators
for the large part, have targeted
whoever is there to prey upon,
whether that's men or women.
- Whenever I'd see that, you know,
there is evidence that another
woman has been sexually assaulted,
the question I keep asking myself is,
"When does this ever end?"
$$ 1991 Navy Tailhook.
- [Newscaster] Breaking news at this hour,the navy appears to be facing
a huge sex scandal. Details are still coming in.
- [Announcer] From ABC, this is
World News Tonight with Peter Jennings.
- Good evening, we're going to begin
tonight by putting a human face
on the worst case of sexual harassment
of the Navy's history.
At an annual Naval Aviators Convention
called, the Tailhook Convention,
Senior officers have known since 1985 that the convention included
the so called, gauntlet, set up for the specific purpose
of targeting and sexually molesting women.
- [Paula Coughlin] I got off the elevator on the third floor.
You could see maybe 200 men.
It was just a few steps into the hallway
before they closed ranks all around me.
And then it happened very quickly,
from both sides and from behind,
men came in and started reaching in my shirt.
I was getting pushed down to the floorand someone was reaching under my skirt
pulling my underwear off, and you know,
and it was about maybe 30 or 40 feet
of 200 guys trying to pull my clothes off,
like I was a high valued target.
The next morning I met with
my boss for breakfast
and I said,
"You know, what happened here?"
And he said,
"That's what you get for walking down
a hallway full of drunk aviators."
And I said, "I don't think so. "
- [Peter Jennings] An investigationwas finally begun,
but 1500 interviews later, the Navy's inspector general reported
that his investigators
were being stone walled.
A great wall of silencehad gone up to protect the guilty.
$$ 1996 Army Aberdeen Proving Grounds
- [Newscaster] The US army today is trying to establish the extent
of a new and growing rapeand sexual harassment scandal.
It all took place at the army base at Aberdeen Proving Ground,
where 30 women have filed complaints of sexual advances
that range from unwanted touching to rape and forcible sodomy.
- [Lt. Gen. Claudia Kennedy] Aberdeen Proving Ground is a location
where the non‐commissioned officers
were assaulting and raping trainees
and then passing the name of the person
they had assaulted to another NCO.
- That's unacceptable conduct
for soldiers,
it's unacceptable to the army
and we have zero tolerance.
$$ 2003 Air Force, Air Force Academy
- [Peter Jennings] Twelve years ago, the Tailhook sex scandal
shook the US Navy and now the Air Force faces
what may be an even bigger problem --
rape and other sexual abuse
at the Air Force Academy
in Colorado Springs.
- 142 allegations of assault against women
have been made in the last decade.
- The highest ranking Air Force generals
knew about serious problems
of sexual assault at the academy,
yet failed to take action.
- We don't intend to sweep this
under the rug, we take it very seriously,
we're going to address it publicly.
- [Newscaster] In congress, outraged senators accused the Air Force brass
of ignoring assaults on women.
- We have a clear pattern of reports
of sexual assault
where the reaction
of the Air Force Academy
seems to be to blame the victim.
- We're in the process of instituting
those changes now.
- [Sen. John McCain] You're in the processof instituting those changes now?
Obviously you and I and the secretary
have a fundamental disagreement here.
$$ Present Day
$$ Secretary of Defense
Confirmation Hearing
- [Sen. Clair McCaskill] What needs to be done and what should be done,
as it relates to the problem of sexual assault within the military,
women in the military that have had
a great deal of difficulty
accessing some sense of justice?
- I really totally
share your concerns. We have to be--
we have to have zero tolerance for any
kinds of sexual assaults in the military.
$$ One mile from the US Capitol Building,
Marine Barracks Washington DC.
- [Announcer] At a small post in Washington DC,
Marine pride, history, and tradition live on.
Marine Barracks at 8th to 9th streets
is the oldest post in the corps and for a hundred years
since the early 1800s,it was Marine Corps headquarters.
♪ [marching music] ♪
- [Donna McAleer] Marine Barracks in Washington DC
is the most prestigious unit there is
in the Marine Corps.
This is the unit where
the best of the best go.
It is the Marine Corps'
showcase ceremonial unit.
It handles presidents and dignitaries. Security at the White House,
the Silent Drill Team.
[rifles clicking]
- After my deployment to
Operation Iraqi Freedom in 2008/2009,
my command officer recommended me for the Marine Barracks in Washington.
I was excited.
It was the tip of the spears
as far as the Marine Crops is concerned.
[rifles clicking]
- She would stay at work late
and then she would drive home
and she would call me and she'd be
on some kind of little high
and she'd talk about how
she loved her job.
She was this sweet person who
was trying really hard in succeeding.
- One of the first things I was told
when I checked in was,
don't wear any makeup because
the marines will all think
that you want to sleep with them.
And I thought, "That's just ridiculous."
- The atmosphere off the bat at
Marine Barracks Washington was horrible.
People asked me what sexual favors
had I performed to get my orders there.
- [Ariana] There was senior officer in my command,
who the first time he spoke to me,he said,
"Female marines here are nothing
but objects for the marines to fuck."
- So, the minute a female
shows up at my work,
she is immediately pounced on.
All of the new females get talked about,
saying that they're having sex,
sleeping with so and so.
Apparently I slept with all these men,
and I mean, I didn't.
- [Ariana] They got progressively worse and worse.
They determined that I welcomed the
sexual harassment by
wearing my regulation length uniform skirt and running in running shorts.
There were several junior female
marines that came up to me crying,
while I was there saying that
they felt too humiliated to come to work.
$$ In units where sexual harassment
is tolerated, incidents of rape triple.
[rifles clicking]
- [Elle Helmer] One of the duties atMarine Barracks Washington,
was a ceremonial drill.
The evening parades are what
you would see on the news.
The sound drill platoon, President,
everybody goes to those type of things.
- After the parades, all of the officers
are required to stay till midnight
and drink at Center Houseat Marine Barracks, Washington.
So, we're talking about Wednesday night happy hours
that start at three and end at two AM.
- It was a partying and drinking culture.
The atmosphere revolved around
going out and partying and drinking.
- I was ordered to drink. I was ordered
to attend the drinking events.
- My boss even said that they
were mandatory to me.
She's like, "We do our best work
at these events."
- [Elle Helmer] We went to various pubs and bars and the goal was
to do a shot at each one,all paid for by the Marine Corps.
- [Ariana] You're talking aboutdrinking events where,
other senior officers are drinkingto the point of peeing in their pants
you know, passing out on lawns.
This is the norm.
- [Elle Helmer] At one bar, I had water, and I was ordered a shot anyway,
and told I needed to take two shots,
to make up for that.
$$ March 16, 2006.
I left the bar to get a cab.
My company commander
followed me and said,
"I need to talk to you
about some things."
So, we walked up the stairs
in to his office.
There was a little bit of a struggle.
He tried to kind of make an advanceand tried to kiss me.
I tried to leave and he slammed
the door on my arms.
I fell on the ground and hit my face on his desk.
And the next thing I realized was
I had woken up wearing his shorts
with all of my clothes off
and in tremendous pain.
I knew enough about me
that something wasn't right
and I had felt entirely violated.
$$ The day after the incident,
NCIS opened an investigation.
$$ It was closed three days later
with no action taken.
$$ Two days later, the base commander
initiated his own investigation.
The colonel at one point said,
"You know, Lieutenant Helmer,
boys girls and alcohol just don't mix.
We'll never really know
what happened inside that office.
Only you and the major know
and he's not talking.
So, at this point, the investigation
is closed for a lack of evidence
and we've reopened a new investigation
against you
for conduct unbecoming of an officer
and public intoxication."
- I remember, we're going to the bar,
and there was an officer that said
he's buying shots for us.
After I've had a couple of drinks,
that's all I remember.
$$ The same officer stalked and raped her
on three separate occasions.
This officer bragged
to his fellow officer friends
that he had 'bagged' me.
I got called up to a major's office
and he charged me
with fraternization and adultery.
He was married, I wasn't,
and I was charged with adultery.
- [Ariana] I told the battalion XO about the humiliation and the comments,
and he said, "You know you should do
what a marine officer should do
and that's to ignore it and move on."
- I used to lie awake in bed, you know,
wondering what I could do
to help her get out.
$$ After a weekly drinking event
in August 2010, Ariana was raped
by a senior officer 3and his friend. $$
- He said that if I told anybody, that
he was going to have his friend Marve
from Indiana kill me
and throw me in a ditch,
because that's how they
take care of things in Indiana.
- [Ben Klay] She went to war and gave nine years of her life,
and for them to take it
and come back and say,
"Yes they called you a whore,
yes they called you a slut,
yes they called you a walking mattress,
it's documented
over and over and over again,
but you deserved it
and when you complained about it,
you were welcoming it."
- The actions of my seniors,
both in the assault and in the ensuing
investigations have really destroyed me.
- [Capt. Ben Klay] When your wifedoesn't come home to --
you rummage through the house
searching for the suicide note,
to call the police with one hand
while you're restraining her
from killing herself with the other.
- [Ariana] I think the thing that makes methe most angry
is not even the rape in itself.
it's the commanders that were complicit
in covering up everything that happened.
$$ The filmmakers contacted
five female marines
$$who were each assaulted
by an officer while serving
$$at Marine Barracks Washington.
$$ Four of the women were investigated
or punished after they reported.
$$No officer was punished for any assault.
- This is an organization that
gives commanders
an unbelievable amount of power.
And I felt it, as a lieutenant in Iraq,
it's scary. You appoint the prosecution,
you appoint the defense,
you appoint the investigator,
you're in charge of the police force,
you're in charge of the community.
You own everything. You are judge,
you are jury, you are executioner.
- Most Americans assume that
there is access to a system of justice,
so that, for example if you're a civilian
and you're raped, you can call the police
and then you have prosecutors,
either federal prosecutors, state
prosecutors, local prosecutors,
that bring the perpetrator to justice.
The problem with the military is that
instead, they have to go
to their chain of command.
- Now in our system of military justice,
it is the commander who's responsible
to the chain of command
for how that investigation proceeds.
- I know that there's been numerous times
over my career that I regretted
that an individual commander
had the total say so over a case.
Most of them don't have the training
or the education to determine
what's appropriate and in serious
felony criminal investigations.
- The problem in the military
is the convening authority
who is not legally trained,
makes the final decision.
[aircraft taking off]
- [Jessica Hinves] They had achange of command at my old squadron
where the guy that raped me
was still stationed.
He had only been in command
for four days,
and he made a decision
over legal to stop the case.
- What I saw was commanders,
and these are field grade officers,
lieutenant colonels, colonels who
have been in 20, 25 years,
they're career officers,
and they sweep cases under the rug.
- The last thing a company commander
in the army wants to do
is make the phone call to his
or her battalion commander to say,
"I have had an allegation of a rape
in my unit."
This is viewed in many cases
as a failure to command
that will adversely then
affect their career.
- Sometimes you would see a guy
get four or five years
for selling a minor amount of drugs.
And then you would see a guy
get two weeks extra duty for rape.
- The military hides behind this notion
that it is really, really hard,
almost impossible to prosecute rape.
But when you look at prosecution ratesin the 2010 Department of Defense reports,
you begin with 2410 unrestricted reportsand 748 restricted.
What that means is they've alreadyfunneled 748 sexual assault victims
into a system that has absolutely no adjudication whatsoever.
Then you take the 2410 that have been reported,
of those they have identified3223 perpetrators.
Now what happens once you send a perpetrator over to command?
Well, the command has just completely unfettered discretion
to do whatever it is they want.
And what is it that they do do?
First off, they drop 910 of them,they just don't do anything.
Then of the 1025 that they actually take some action,
do they court martial them?
No. Only half of them, 529,actually got court martialed.
The rest 256 were subjected toArticle 15 punishments,
109 to administrative discharges,
and 131 to "other adverse administrative actions,"
whatever the heck that means.
And then of the convictionswhere they actually get jail time,
when you work your way all the way through the numbers,
what you're looking at, is that out of 3223 perpetrators,
only 175 end up doingany jail time whatsoever.
- [Louise Slaughter] I have beenin congress for seven terms now,
and every single term,
we have had meetings with D.O.D
and they come in and they confirm
to us, we're going to be serious.
We're going to take care of this,
we're going to stop this, zero tolerance.
But the rhetoric is not being turned
into the reality of protecting our women,
and in some cases men in our military.
- They were like, but we have this SARC
and SAPRO program.
It's like, oh great...
What does that do?
They can strongly suggest to the military to do something.
- [Announcer] As a band of brothersand sisters, it is our personal duty
to prevent sexual assault.
- They can't order them, they can't
enforce it, they don't back it up.
- In April of this year, we will debut
a social marketing campaign
as part of our prevention strategy.
- [Female Voice] Preventing sexual assault is part of my duty.
- [Male Voice] So when I saw my buddy's date was drunk, I told him,
"Ask her when she's sober."
- It's ludicrous, you know,
it's the year 2011
and we have posters that say,
"Wait until she's sober."
And it's remarkable that that's allowed
to pass in today's military.
- Well, we've implemented training at
each and every level of military service.
From the moment they enter
the service in basic training,
they're given that.
And our campaign consists of a series of posters that are actually
training tools and each of those posters has a different focus.
- You cannot prevent sexual assault
with pretty posters.
Posters do not prevent sexual predators
from preying upon women
and men in the military.
We're talking about barging into rooms
in the middle of the night.
No poster can prevent a criminal
from barging into a room.
These are violent people.
- One of the things that we do
in our prevention strategy
is to focus on bystander intervention.
And in that strategy and in that training
we ask for each soldier or sailor,
airman and marine,
to be aware of what sexual assault is
and how to prevent it.
- SARC is a joke.
The things that they say are ignored
or they're made fun of.
♪ [music] ♪
- There may be a video, or 20 slides.
It's like a lot of military training
where it's the once of the year,
check in a box.
♪ [music] ♪
- SAPRO can't fix anything.
- [Man] You walkin' back alone?
- [Woman] Yeah,
It's just a short walk to my tube.
- [Man] Alright.
- [Capt. Bhagwati] And all the money seems to be spent on advertising,
which is just rife with victim blaming.
- [Man] What's your name?
- [Woman] Hey, stop.
- [Man] Hey, come here, come here.
I wanna talk to you for a second.
I just wanna talk to you.
[running footsteps]
- [Man] Whoa! Are you okay?
- [Woman] No. There's this guy,
he grabbed me.
- [Man] Why are you by yourself?
Where's your buddy?
- [Woman] I didn't think I needed one.
[Narrator] Sexual Assault is preventable.
Are you doing your part?
- And so this notion that, you know,
essentially, anyone could be a rapist,
we all have to be on alert,
it misses an opportunity
to take real steps towards
preventing rape.
If they actually had systems
of accountability that prosecuted
and imprisoned perpetrators,
you would get rid of
a lot of the rapes right away.
- [Kirby] How would you characterize the typical sex offender?
- Well, if I look at our data from
the Department of Defense,
it is young people that are
ages 18 to 24 or 25.
[Kirby] Would you say that most of them are serial rapists?
- I don't have data one way or another
to determine that.
- [Kirby] And what percentage of the rapes do you think
are caused by serial predators?
- I don't -- I don't have any numbers.
I don't know how to -- I don't think
we collect that type of data.
- [Kirby] There have been studies done,
that people who enter the military aretwice as likely to have committed rape
as the equivalent populationin the civilian world.
- I'm not aware of that study.
My area of expertise focuses primarily
on prevention and victim care.
- [Kirby] But wouldn't prevention include focusing on the perpetrators?
$$ July 31, 2008, Kaye Whitley
is subpoenaed to testify
$$ before the House Subcommittee on
National Security and Foreign Affairs.
[Congress Chairman] I noticed thatDr. Kaye Whitley is not in her chair.
Is it under your direction that she
is not showing
for testimony this morning?
- [Michael Dominguez] Yes sir.
- You directed her not to?
- [Michael Dominguez] I did.
- Do you have an executive
privilege to assert?
- No, Sir.
- You've instructed her not to come?
What is your reason for doing that?
- If you find the department's response
and prevention efforts fall short
of your expectations,
responsibility for that shortfall
rests with me.
- [Rep. Henry A. Waxman] That's a ridiculous answer.
What is it you're trying to hide?
We all remember Tailhook
and the scandal,
and how the military tried
to cover that up.
I don't know who you think elected you
to defy the Congress of the United States.
We're an independent branch
of government.
- So for now Mr. Dominguez,
you are dismissed.
[footsteps]
- [Kori] Intimacy is definitely affected. We'll go months without sex.
I have to initiate, if I'm comfortable
enough, if I'm having a good day,
and I think my husband looks hot
for the day, I have to initiate.
When he comes and hugs me,
sometimes I'll cringe
and I'll just want him to --
you know, like,
he'll feel it, and then he'll get mad
because he didn't --
"Why aren't you hugging me back?"
or whatever.
- I still do that. There's times I --
- I don't like him grabbing my hips.
- I didn't understand, you know, why
because it's like I'm you're husband.
And l don't fully understand now.
- [Kori] I see it in my dreams.
That's what you don't get,
I don't want to talk about stuff,
and you know that.
- Yeah, but that's the hard part,
I don't know --
I want to help you, but I don't know,
you know?
- What?
- What? I guess...
- You can't help me.
That's the thing, 'cause you can't.
- [Kori] Sometimes I think, if when he has sex with me,
is he thinking about me getting raped,
is he upset, is he, you know,
because I think about that, and never
does it not run through my head.
That's why I didn't want to have sex for a while.
- What if you were in my spot?
- It would suck so bad.
I'm not saying I don't appreciate you,
I mean, I'm crying. Maybe this way,
I can express it to you, Rob,
because it does upset me.
[sobbing]
Like when we almost split up
'cause of stuff,
and I feel like I'm responsible for it.
I don't know what I'd do if I lost Rob.
I don't... I'd be so lost.
He's like my only supporter.
Like my own blood.
- [Amy Herdy] I've interviewed womenin the civilian world,
and rape is a very, very traumatizing
thing to have happened,
but I've never seen trauma
like I've seen from women
who are veterans who have suffered
military sexual trauma.
- I cannot remember how many times
a young female marine
that had been raped
or sexually assaulted had told me
that she looked at these guys
as her brother, or the suspect
as her brother.
- It's akin to what happens
in a family with incest.
Because, you know, in the military,
when we're functioning at our best
in a cohesive unit with brothers
and sisters, you know,
the band of brothers and sisters,
I mean we are family.
When that bond of trust is violated,
the wound penetrates to the very most
inner part of one's soul, one's psyche.
- [Kori Cioca] I have this folderthat I keep.
I have all my bootcamp letters in it,
from my mom and my sisterand people and...
I was just going through some
of the stuff and I'm like, "What's this?"
When I opened it up, I'm like,
"Oh my god, my suicide letter."
Mom, I'm sorry for the grief that you must feel.
Just because I'm gone physically
doesn't mean
I won't be there spiritually.
I truly feel that God willtake me without question,
even though I took my own life.
I've had the most broken thoughts,
dreams, and physical pain to remind me
of the horrific acts upon methat happened while on duty.
A mother, brother, sister and husband should never live
with knowing the horrible acts upon me.
Find peace in knowing that the bodyleft behind doesn't consume my soul.
I am free now, and I'm not afraid.
Ready to soar, Kori Danielle.
- [Trina McDonald] I took a whole bottle of pills.
And woke up strangely enough,
I'm not sure why. [chuckles]
At that point in my life
I just wanted it to be over.
I think I was 20, 21 and then
within the next year, I tried again.
- I went out into the garage,
which was separate from the house,
and I turned the car on.
I was going to sit in the car
and asphyxiate myself.
And we have this little poodle,
Blondie.
She went out in the little doggy door
and she's scratching
and howling at the door.
I said, "Shut up, Goddammit!
You're going to wake my wife up."
So I got out, shut the car off,
and I thought for a minute,
I'll just take her in the garage with me.
Then, I said, "Why would you kill a dog?
That's stupid."
And then it dawned on me,
"Why would you kill yourself?"
- I thought of it, so many times,
and in so many ways.
I thought about at one point in time,
hanging myself from the flagpole,
with a sign on me saying exactly
what happened, to make him feel bad.
- I was gonna overdose
on pain medication
and sleeping medication,
and just hope that I would fall asleep
and my body would just shut down,
or do something.
When I went to the doctor,
I had been feeling sick,
and dizzy and nauseated,
and they took my urine
and they told me that I was pregnant.
And it was like, there's a life in there,
you know.
And maybe her life
will be better than mine,
and I've got to make sure of that.
So, she's very special.
- [Brigadier Wilma Vaught] Sometimes it takes a different kind of action
to cause change to come,
and sometimes that's a lawsuit.
-[Susan Burke] I grew up on military basesMy dad was career army.
When I was a child, when we answered the phone,
we used to have to say,"Colonel Burke's quarters,"
[chuckles]
and because of that,
I have an understanding of the level
of control that the military exercises
that perhaps most
in the civilian life don't have.
The Feres Doctrineis a judicial doctrine
that was developed bythe Supreme Court that says,
if you're in the military, you cannot suefor something that happens to you
that's incident to your military service.
If your military doctor amputatethe wrong limb,
you are out of luck, you cannot sue
for that harm that's been done to you.
So, we filed a law suit in federal courton behalf of 16 men and women,
seeking to bring
former Secretary Rumsfeld
and Secretary Gates to justice.
- I heard about the lawsuit
and decided to become a part of it
because I never wanted
another woman
to go through what I went through.
$$ - How have you been feeling emotionally about doing this?
- Oh, I've been so sick, like just sick
to my stomach.
And I think right now, I'm just
kind of like, just get there.
I'm like numbing myself just
to get there.
And then I know when I get there,
it should -- I don't know.
[Susan Burke] The law suit alleges
that they have overseen
a system that has deprived the rape
survivors of their constitutional rights,
specifically we alleged
that they deprived them
of their substantive due process,
procedural due process,
equal protection
and First Amendment rights.
[Kori] It made me sick to see everybody's stories.
How they kind of closely tie together.
Everybody's story somehow has a --
It's consistent, like what
the military does to people like us.
- All the things that they've put in place
are all pretty much intended
to help women deal
with being raped better,
that's what they're about.
- I joined the military halfway through
my senior year of high school,
wanting to serve my country
and do new things
and challenge myself in a different way.
I was in the army about sevenor eight years
before anything ever happened to me.
I was raped by another CID agent
who was senior to me.
I was contacted by an agent
with Fort Riley CID,
who said they were investigating
the suspect as a serial rapist
who had raped several military
law enforcement women.
I thought, there was no way that,
you know, he wouldn't be convicted.
If I have a difficult time with anything,
it's about the fact that I had
an almost ten-year career
which I was very invested in, and
I gave it all up to report a sex offender
who was not even put to justice
or put on the registry,
and he's probably doing
the same thing right now.
- I had one female lieutenant
pull me aside
and tell me that, you know,
she had heard about my case
and she thought she could talk to me
as one female marine to another,
and she told me,
"Well, what he did, was capitalize on an
opportunity that you presented him."
"That's not the same thing as rape,
you need to know that."
I think, a month after it happened,
they made me go on a hike with him,
and I tried having everybody advocate
for me to not make me go
because I just couldn't deal
with seeing him.
So their solution to that
was to put him in front of me,
so that I could see him the whole time.
So that I could know where he was
and know that he
wasn't able to do anything
because he was standing
right in front of me.
And I remember thinking the entire time
we were up on the hills,
up at Camp Pendleton,
if only it was steeper,
I would have jumped.
- There's no way out of it,
I mean if you think about it,
the only way out of it
is like suicide or AWOL.
Those are your only two options.
Suicide, AWOL or deal with it.
- Right now, I'm just barely
appreciating
learning how to appreciate
being a woman again.
That's 11 years,
and I'm trying to have fun with it,
not forcing myself to have fun.
I'm trying really hard not to cry
but it just pisses me off.
Watching you girls having to go
through what I have
it makes me want to explode.
- Being here, knowing that
me wanting to commit suicide,
I'm not alone. Me being hit and raped,
I'm not alone. Everything --
the way that they treated me, the way
that they made me feel, I'm not alone.
And we have all of you guys, with all
of your knowledge and everything
you guys are going to stand right up,
you know, that's awesome.
That's all I'm saying.
- I think the women who are
coming forward
in this law suit are very courageous,
because they're putting their names
out there for criticism;
they're putting their names out there
to go down in history
as they were the ones who got raped,
and that isn't anything you want
to go through life with.
[people bustling]
- [Capt. Anu Bhagwati] Today I standin solidarity with the courageous
women and men who have served in
our nation's our armed forces.
The inspirational plaintiffs
you see before you are a small handful
of the tens of thousands
of troops and veterans
who have been sexually brutalized
by their fellow service members
while defending our nation.
It is time to finally acknowledge
that our military's judicial system
is broken when it comes to these cases.
- [Kori] My name is Kori Cioca
and in my case, my commandwas unwilling to help me.
I went for help many times with other
petty officers and I was denied help,
even with other men saying,
"Please get her away from him."
and it was still allowed.
- My name is Sarah Albertson.
People were telling me,
"Don't go to the public."
"Don't let this get out because
it will make the military look bad."
- I really feel like it is
my social responsibility
to speak out about this issue,
especially considering my
investigative experience and the fact
that the military justice system
allows so many offenders
to escape justice.
[applause]
[people chattering]
- [Kori] She's actually starting
to play with her toys.
- Yeah, imaginative playing and stuff.
- But it's all the stuff
that you teach them
if you notice, like, when they play.
You know, it's really cool.
- Yeah.
- I miss my baby.
- I do, too.
♪ [music[ ♪
- [Kori] Thank you for having us.
- Sure. Thanks for being willing to
fill me in a little bit
on some of the experiences.
- My name is Regina Vazquez
and I served honorably
in the United States Marine Corps
for four years.
- My name is Kori Cioca and I served in
the United States Coast Guard.
I was harassed and sexually assaulted.
- I was administratively
discharged with no benefits
after nine and a half years of service.
- Women should not bear that burden.
That is not part of what we should have
to be doing to be doing our jobs.
- We're talking about criminal activity.
We're talking about a vicious attack
that is criminal. It is an assault.
[Myla Haider] Almost none of the cases
made it to court‐martial,
and out of the ones that do,
almost none of them result in conviction.
- It seems to me all the times
that I've looked at these things
that the command is the one
who has such so much discretion.
- I think the advocate
should actually be civilians.
Not ones that work in the military.
I think we should have actual units,
civilian units.
- It absolutely tears in my inside
to think that this has been going on
for as long as it's been going on
and we've never addressed it.
- All people in the military must know,
if you're a perpetrator of sexual assault
against someone else in the military,
woe be to you.
You're going to be held accountable.
- [Myla Haider] As a CID agent, I found it tremendously frustrating
when I would demonstrate that
an offender had committed an offense,
and taking it to a commander
and having a commander
be the deciding authority.
You know, I don't think commanders
are capable
of making an objective decision.
I do not think it should be in their hands.
- So you would suggest taking
the discretion away from them?
- [Myla Haider] Yes, absolutely.
- [Rep. Niki Tsongas]
Congresswoman Davis and I
are both on the
armed services committee.
- There are a number of issues
that you've raised
that makes me want to go back
and particularly take another look.
- On an emotional one,
individual basis,
what happens after a crime like
that has been committed
is a very difficult thing to go through,
and don't think I don't know. I know.
- The fact that you're willing to tell me
your stories first hand,
makes it much easier for us to go back
and to say you know these are policies
we have to change.
It's a big deal what you're doing.
- We rarely find people like you,
who stand up for us,
and just thank you so much
for everything that you do.
- Very nice to meet you all.
- Nice to meet you.
- Thank you again for your service.
- Thanks for your time.
- Mr. Speaker, last year,
the military received over 3000 reports
of sexual assault involving
other members in the service.
This week, 17 veterans are saying
that the military ignored their cases
of sexual assault
while they were on active duty.
- Today I'm going to talk about
seaman Kori Cioca
who served in the Coast Guard
from August 2005 to June 2007.
She now suffers from PTSD
and an abnormal EEG
due to nerve damage in her face.
Cioca later told the press,
"It's like they didn't care."
"It wasn't important,
I wasn't important."
- [Kori] So, we're eating at Bob Evans
and we overhear a girl
talking about getting ready
to go into the military,
so I go over there and try to talk to her.
Has anybody told you what to
watch for or anything?
- [Waitress] My boyfriend's in the navy.
- [Kori] So, he knows how tough
it is for women.
- [Waitress] Yeah, he's been in
for a couple of months now.
- [Kori] So, how does he feel
about you joining?
Like, isn't he scared that the men
will do something?
- [Waitress] He's a little scared but
he knows I can take care of myself.
- [Kori] Oh I thought so too,
so be careful.
- [Waitress] Yeah.
- I definitely let her know that maybeshe should reconsider college
and getting a degree.
It'll save her some of the trouble.
I wish someone would have told me that.
You try to take care okay?
You can still back out.
You can be a civilian worker.
- [Waitress] Yeah, thank you. I'm not signed yet.
- [Kori] Okay, well, just be careful.
- [Miette Wells] People always ask me, "Was it worth it going in?"
The idea of it is honorable.
Serving your country is great.
There are great people in it,
and then there are people
who will end up ruining your life.
- [Ariana] Just the other day,
I saw a girl running along the road.
She looked like she
was about high school age.
She was wearing a USMC T‐shirt,
and I thought that, if she joins,
then she's going to have to accept rape
and destruction of her life.
I cannot in good faith,
I cannot recommend
anyone to join with the way
the organization is set up now.
I would not wish that on anyone.
- [Rep. Chellie Pingree] You can't askwomen to serve and then say,
"Oh by the way, if you get in one
of these horrendous situations,
we won't be there to back you up
or to help you."
- When I would do nominations
for the Air Force Academy,
you know, it was difficult to talk
to parents and say,
"Don't worry, if you send her here.
she's not going to get raped."
- No. I would tell my daughter
not to join the military.
They have good things to offer
but a rape is not one of them.
- Not in my lifetime.
She's not joining, no.
- I would be terrified if my daughter
wanted to join the military.
I would have a serious long talk
with here and hopefully, she'd --
the one thing is
that's what she'd listen to.
- Losing even one soldier,
needlessly
because of military sexual
trauma, is one too many.
[dog barking]
- [Kori] I'm going to get the mail.
- [Rob] Okay
- Fingers crossed.
Here's my fate.
[envelope flap ripping]
- [Rob] What does it say?
-Umm...
Effective October 20th 2009.
My overall combined rating is 70%.
Wait. Service connection
for anxiety is denied,
service connection for disk placement
and bilateral disk displacement
is denied.
Those motherfuckers, man.
Oh, my god.
- [Baby] Mommy!
- I'll be right there, Shey.
My face doesn't have any disks in it,
that's what the x‐rays show.
That's what Dr. Carper's letter show.
- How can you deny medical for --
I mean, when there's x‐rays?
[Baby talking]
- [Kori] What?
- Who's coming?
[Baby talking]
- Uh-huh, I will.
- If you do not agree with our decision
you should write us and tell us why.
- 'Cause you're an asshole.
- And you should identify specific issues.
- You're an idiot.
- The evidence that was reviewed
showed that you served, whatever
which is less than minimum
active duty requirements
for disability pension.
But it wasn't your choice.
- They're going to punish me
for what they did,
because I was short two months
of two years.
[Baby talking]
I know, I feel the same way, Shea.
- [Dr. Kaye Whitley] It's nice to seeyou again and thank you for coming.
You have been provided highlights
of the numbers of the report
and I'll walk you through those slides,
then I'm going to play a short
public service announcement
and then we can entertain questions.
I think the prevention aspect
of sexual assault
goes back in some ways
to risk reduction.
- [Kirby] What is risk reduction?
[Dr. Kaye Whitley] Risk reductions
are ideas like telling women to --
if they're going to go somewhere,
together,
always have a buddy with them.
- [Kirby] Are there other examplesof risk reduction?
- I'm not familiar, but that's out
of my area of expertise.
$$ August 1, 2011,
Major General Mary Kay Hertog
$$replaces Kaye Whitley as the Director of
the Sexual Assault and Prevention Office.
- [Major Gen. Mary Kay Hertog] Well,
I want to continue
where Dr. Whitley left off.
Looking at where our focus is and that's
on prevention as well as response,
we've really done a very good job there
and the credit goes to Dr. Whitley
and her staff that has been working this
the last five to years years.
- I don't think the Department of Defense
has really yet embraced that they have
a sexual assault problem.
That it's not just an issue
of a cultural environment
or that the people at risk
for sexual assault.
That their system itself, though, just
does not value the rights of victims
and doesn't provide them
adequate protection.
- You know, I have heard
the accusations as well,
that you know, commanders
are sweeping this under the carpet.
Now, what I would say to the people
that have come forward to you is,
if you feel that your commander is
ignoring what you have asked them to do,
if they are not taking care of you
within that chain of command,
you need to go to the DOD,
the Department of Defense
Inspector General.
- The GAO, General Accounting Office,
just did a study, a report
and guess what -- not one, not one case,
of more than 2500 has been reviewed
and investigated by the Inspector General,
and when asked about that,
the Inspector General said,
"Well, we have other higher priorities."
- What you really want is you want
there to be a system akin
to a civilian system
where you go to the police
and the crime is prosecuted
by an impartial judicial system.
- As a commander, you have no favorites.
You are equally to take care
of every single person
in your organization.
That's what command is all about.
- These are human beings
just like everyobody else.
You cannot be impartial when you are
already involved
with people in other settings.
- I would take exception
with your characterization
that the disposition of the case
is based on the relationship
between the commander
and the alleged perpetrator.
$$ 33% of female soldiers
didn't report their rape
$$ because the person to report to
was a friend of the rapist.
- I'm going to speak to you
with my former commander's hat on.
There is absolutely
no conflict of interest.
You do what the right thing is to do.
$$ 25% of the female soldiers
didn't report their rape
$$ because the person to report to
is the rapist.
You have other avenues
and if you feel like
you have not been
taken care of adequately
by your commander,
go up through your congressman,
or congresswoman,
file a complaint that way.
- You can't go to your congressman
to obtain justice for being raped,
I mean, imagine how silly that is,
imagine if you told civilians that,
"Oh geez, sorry you were raped,
go talk to your congressman."
$$ Many of our closest NATO allies
no longer allow commanders
$$ to determine the prosecution
of sexual assault cases.
- [Amy] If you could say something to this guy,
what would you want to say to him?
- I don't know. I don't think
it's affected his life at all.
And people in my old squadron
that I've talked to,
they don't see any effect that this had
on him, and that hurts
because it's a struggle every day
and it's completely changed who I am.
[sobbing]
- I'm really hoping he falls off the
Coast Guard boat and they never find him.
I'm really hoping for that.
Or there's a poor mishap
and got chopped up by the prop.
- That would be great.
- That would be an exciting day.
- It would. I'd probably celebrate.
- Right?
- Yeah.
- I hope this reaches them too, you know.
I hope that somewhere, someone
sees my face,
you know, wherever it is, and goes,
"I know them and they're talking
about me,"
because they know what they did,
you know.
And then all they'll have to mutter
is to some friend that goes,
"Hey weren't we stationed with her?"
You know, and then they can't be
a secret anymore.
So hopefully they have to
deal with it, too, you know,
in some way, shape or form.
- Most rapists are repetitive criminals.
It's a kind of crime
that has an obsessive quality
so people do it again and again.
So the tragedy of that is
that every one of these guys
who gets off freely, will be doing it
to other women, again and again,
often for years and years and years.
- The average sex offender
in their lifetime has about 300 victims,
and the vast majority of sex offenders
will never be caught.
- A lot of civilians see it as being
a military problem, but it really isn't.
Because 5% or less
of reported offenders are convicted,
so almost none of them wind up
on the sex offender registry.
- There is no military sex offender list
that I'm aware of,
but if you're convicted in court,
a felony conviction of sex offense
of a sex offense, you're going
to go on the national list.
- [Kirby] For any sex offense whatsoever?
- Correct.
- That is not the case. It depends on
what level of conviction they got.
If they received over a year,then that's considered a felony.
But a lot of these cases are plead down,
so that they're not felonies.
The military doesn't like
to prosecute people
and keep them as felony convictions.
- I often ask myself the question,
"Why would they stop?"
And if there's nothing to stop them
like incarceration,
or some other major life change,
they're going to continue.
- [Stace Nelson] If you run a sexual predator
through the judicial system and thenyou give him slap him on the hand,
all you've done, is you've done theequivalent of catch and release program.
You've caught them, you've educated them,
and now you've released them backinto hometown America.
He now knows a lot more
about the law enforcement,
the judicial system, than he did
when he first started,
which makes him a much more
capable criminal,
and a much more dangerous criminal.
- They go on to literally prey
on women and men
in our neighborhoods
across the United States.
If we don't care about
women and men in the military,
then we should hopefully care
about women and men, girls and boys
in our neighborhood back home.
$$ In December 2011, the Court
dismissed the survivors' lawsuit
$$ ruling that rape is an occupational
hazard of military service.
$$ An appeal has been filed.
[camera clicking]
- [Woman] There you go.
- [Helen Benedict] The thing that broke my heart
heart more than anything about this story,
was the young women who went in
with such idealism,
I want to serve my country, I want to give back.
To see a young person's hope and idealism crushed in that brutal way,
I think we owe our young peoplemore than that.
- Increasingly, women are becoming
some of the best‐trained professionals
that we have in the military.
These are great soldiers and we can't afford to lose them.
- Yeah, I'm happy to never have
to wear that again.
- People deeply believe in their hearts
to serve their country.
They should be given that chance,
with respect.
[camera clicking]
You know, it's part of really
our American way.
- [Kori] Do you think we deserve
a purple heart
because we were wounded
in a time of war?
- [Regina] They're never going
to give us one.
- [Kori] I know, but I'm just saying
maybe there should be a ribbon
for women who --
- have served their country --
- who have survived it, you know.
- survived it.
- We have a good army, a good military,
but not a great one
and this is the kind of issue that keeps
our military from being great.
- We can view this as a shared challenge.
It's not just a woman's issue,
it's not just something
the military has to deal with,
but as society,
we're all in this together.
[camera clicking]
It's our national duty.
$$ Five, years after her attack,
Kori is still trying to get coverage
$$ for her jaw surgery from the
Veterans Administration.
$$Her assailant is still in the Coast Guard
and lives in Charleston, South Carolina.
$$ Ariana is pursuing her Masters Degree
in Social Work to help survivors
$$ or military sexual assault.
Her assault was court‐martialed
$$ and found guilty of adultery and
indecent language.
$$ Elle is working for a corporation
and lives in South Carolina.
$$ Her assailant has recently been
promoted to lieutenant colonel.
$$ Michael and his wife are helping
promote awareness
$$ of male military sexual assault.
$$He does not know the identity
of his assailants
$$ or where they are today.
$$ Jessica and her husband had a baby boy
and are raising him in Virginia.
$$Her assailant is still in the Air Force
and was awarded 'Airman of the Year'
$$ during her rape investigation.
$$ Hannah's father, Jerry,
is returning from Iraq
$$ after a one‐year deployment.
Her assailant is still in the Navy
$$ and stationed three hours
from her home in Kentucky.
$$ Myla's assailant became a supervisor
at a major U.S. corporation
$$ and sexually assaulted a
female employee.
$$ He was never charged
and now lives in Queens, New York.
$$ May 7, 2013
$$ The Department of Defense
released its annual sexual assault report.
$$In 2012, 26,000 women and men were
sexually assaulted in the US military.
$$ A 35% increase over 2011
$$ Go to NotInvisible.org
$$ to demand Washington do more
to stop this epidemic.
$$ Join the conversation
#NotInvisible
$$ Become part of the campaign
to protect those who protect us.
$$ Let them know they are not invisible.
$$ invisible.
♪ [music] ♪